<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Kelaʻ le-dor a compend of the covenant of grace as the most solid support under the most terrible conflicts of death, though arm'd with desertion, decay of grace, and sense of guilt / by Walter Cross.</title>
            <author>Cross, Walter, M.A.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35172</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7258</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27629</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09989131</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09989131</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44461</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35172)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44461)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1328:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Kelaʻ le-dor a compend of the covenant of grace as the most solid support under the most terrible conflicts of death, though arm'd with desertion, decay of grace, and sense of guilt / by Walter Cross.</title>
                  <author>Cross, Walter, M.A.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Barnard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Grace (Theology)</term>
               <term>Covenant theology.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44461:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> A COMPEND OF THE <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> AS The moſt Solid SUPPORT under the moſt Terrible CONFLICTS OF DEATH, THOUGH Arm'd with Deſertion, Decay of Grace, and Senſe of Guilt.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Walter Croſs,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Barnard,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:44461:2"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>fluence of Example and Praiſe, to make them good and virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. 3. The Mouths of thoſe are ſtopt whoſe Duty it is to take all ſuch Opportunities to recover a degenerate Age from Hopes of Glory or Honour at Death, who glory in their Shame when they Live. But the Abuſe of a Natural and Neceſſary Duty, ought not to remove totally its uſe; it's engraven on the very Nature of Man to ſpeak well of the Dead. By the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Cuſtom a Bride takes place of a King, but a Corps takes place of both. <hi>Lev.</hi> 10.18. The Mourning for the Dead takes place of poſitive External Worſhip: <hi>Moſes</hi> was ſatisfied when <hi>Aaron</hi> told him the Reaſon of not Eating the Sacrifice in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Place, was becauſe of his Grief for the Death of his Sons: And what is the Language of Morning for the Dead but Praiſing of them? Sorrow is a Paſſion rais'd from the Apprehenſion of the Loſs of a great good; and not to Lament the Dead is next to leave them without Burial, as Dung upon the Earth, <hi>Jer.</hi> 16.14. The Dead have not their <hi>Juſta</hi> duely paid them, when no Tears are mingled with their Duſt; the Goſpel that wipes away all Tears from all Eyes, only mitigates this, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Sorrow not as thoſe who have no hope</hi> of ever meeting again. Chriſt himſelf wept over a <hi>Lazarus</hi> that he could and did raiſe again preſently; but as to more remote Relatives or Friends, it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns Sympathy, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.15. <hi>Weep with them that weep.</hi> Tho' the <hi>Egyptians</hi> hated <hi>Iſrael,</hi> they mourned over a dead <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 15.10. ſo that the <hi>Canaanites</hi> call'd the Place <hi>Abel Mizra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im,</hi> the Weeping of the <hi>Egyptians.</hi> How unnatural are the Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of thoſe Children and other Relatives, that the Poſſeſſion that they ſucceed to, drowns the Sorrow and prevents the due Performance of Honour to the Deceaſed, who have ſpent their Lives, if not Sold their Souls for an Eſtate to them. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever others do, they ought to be zealous of keeping their Names ſavoury and freſh. Forreigners, Aliens, will Commend the Names of their Founders. But</p>
            <p>Theſe four Rules ſeem to be drawn from the moſt pure Fountains of Nature, guided by the moſt powerful Conduct of Reaſon. <hi>Confutius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>To ſhun all Oſtentation and Magnificence in Funerals,</hi> that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of Pride and Vanity.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:44461:2"/>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Not to bewail the Dead with Exceſs, or be overcome with Grief;</hi> that beſpeaks want of Reaſon, and more the want of Piety, and ſubmiſſion to our Sovereign Lord.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Not to extinguiſh Grief totally, or hide the Profeſſion or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of it;</hi> for the want of Natural Affection is a deſperate Condition, and no Perſon can expect faithful Friendſhip from that Man, that can bury his Love and Duty to his Friend or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative, and his Memory and Eſteem of him with his Corps.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That Applauſes or Encomiums are the proper Duty of Friends, Neighbours, or more diſtant Relations:</hi> Modeſty ſhou'd ſuppreſs it in Husband, Wife or Children, except to intimate Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, for that is but Praiſing themſelves: Others ought not to be ſilent: The Law of God allow'd an Office for it once. In this Caſe the Modeſty of Relatives has ſuppreſs'd a Name that deſerves to be wrote in Letters of Gold; but it ſuited the Perſon's Temper, that rather would have a Name in Heaven than Fame on Earth, and would have it reſt with the Duſt, and be ſilent as the Grave until that glorious Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>A Second Reſtraint is, that it's Miniſters Duty to Preach a dead and a riſen Chriſt; his Will and Teſtament is the Goſpel we ought to Preach; our Office is making of his Funeral Sermons. <hi>R.</hi> 1. Chriſt is willing that his Saints ſhare of his glory, while it is an exalting of his own alſo. The manifeſtation of Chriſt's Care of his Saints, is much for his Glory. Conſider the <hi>Patience of Job,</hi> and the <hi>End of the Lord.</hi> When a Man has been an envi'd, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted Man for the profeſſion of Truth, and dyes in peace, leaving his Family in Plenty and Proſperity, it is a clear de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of Chriſt's Care of his faithful Servants, and his juſt Reſentment of the Indignation done to them; when we may obſerve an inviſible Moth conſuming the Eſtates of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and an inviſible Worm gnawing their Conſciences.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Deſtruction is threatned to them who obſerve not the Diſpenſations of Divine Providence, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.3. And,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Rods have as obſervable a Nature as any, they have a ſignificant Voice, that every wiſe Man ſhould underſtand, <hi>Mic.</hi> 6. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.14.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Death is as great a Judgment as can be: When Plague, Sword, Famine, come on a Nation or City, it's but Death ſtill; but tho' the Death of the Wicked be the greateſt Judgment, a frequent Death of the Righteous is the greateſt Prodigy, <hi>Iſa.</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:44461:3"/>57.1. <hi>The Righteous periſh and no Man layeth it to Heart — Not knowing they are taken away from the evil to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The Death of the Righteous at this Day is as determin'd in its Language as ever, and more, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13. <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>from henceforth:</hi> I ſhall give this Paraphraſe of it, according to my imperfect Scheme of that Book. We are now about the time of the Death of the Witneſſes, which tho' it be a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere ſtroke to the Militant Church, a time of Faith and Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for the Saints, (the repeating of that Index, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.13. a great Earthquake in <hi>Sicily,</hi> is ſuch an Argument for it, that I know not how we can disbelieve it, without ſaying God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns to deceive us in his Providence, which is the beſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (by fulfillment) of theſe Prophecies, for a greater ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was: The Deſtruction of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> tho' it hath ſome Likeneſs, yet no Equality nor Proportion to it, whether we compare the number of Cities, People, or ſulphureous Lakes, the Largeneſs of the place, or the Dreadfulneſs of the Manner; beſide another <hi>Vulcan</hi> new erected, or a mouth of Hell open'd) yet it is an Harveſt for the Triumphant, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.15. God is now gathering all the Righteous out of the Earth, that he may ſet the Earth on flames. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.18. <hi>The Angel that has power over fire:</hi> This Fire is the Wine-preſs of Divine Wrath, wherein the Wicked are to be trod down. <hi>Lot</hi> muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from <hi>Sodom,</hi> before the ſulphureous Flames be kindled. The Harveſt of the Righteous muſt precede the Vintage of the Wicked; the Salt of the Earth muſt be gone, before its Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption come. There was a Spring-time of the Goſpel in the Apoſtles time, the Summer of Perſecution follow'd: Now is the Harveſt, and the Winter to the Wicked is at the Door.</p>
            <p>But it is more than time to return to my Text, the firſt Verſe whereof affords this Doctrine: <q>That the Spirit of God doth often immediately pen the Praiſes of the Righteous at their Death, and write their Elegies.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The man who was raiſed ap on high, the Anoynted of the God of Jacob, the ſweet Pſalmiſt of Iſrael.</hi> Some Commentators expound all the fourth Verſe to be of this nature, and to have <hi>David</hi> for the ſubject. It is very obſervable, that not only the great men that are wicked, are often buried in Oblivion, as the moſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44461:3"/>of the Monarchs of the firſt and greateſt Empire, but ſome good men too: God induſtriouſly (<hi>Deut.</hi> 34.6.) hides the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre and obſcures the Tomb of a great <hi>Moſes,</hi> while he erects Monuments of Praiſe and Records of Memorial for the mean and Low, who have been Faithful in their Generation; <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.8. <hi>Debora</hi> an aged Woman, and but a Nurſe, muſt have an <hi>Allon Bachuth,</hi> an <hi>Oak of Weeping</hi> erected for her, and the Epitaph muſt have a room made for it in Sacred Writ: So muſt <hi>Eliezers</hi> Fidelity, and <hi>Dorcas</hi>'s Coats of Charity, the Bed, Table, Stool and Candleſtick for the Prophet, the Barley gleanings, the parched Corn and Vinegar, <hi>Ebedmelech</hi>'s Clouts, <hi>Rahabs</hi> ſtalks of Flax, the Widows Mite, and the Womans Alabaſter box of Oyntment. Should not we be followers of God in this alſo?</p>
            <p>The ſecond Obſervation from the Text, is, <hi>Gods great Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy towards David in the Circumſtances of his Death;</hi> not only that ſuch a Man of War ſhould dye in Peace, but ſhould enjoy the uſe of his Underſtanding and Tongue to the laſt, yea the conduct of the Holy Spirit for the Guidance and Direction of both. <hi>Theſe are the laſt Words of David. The Spirit of the Lord ſpake by me, and his Word was in my Tongue;</hi> the whole of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. witneſſeth further, wherein is contained his laſt Prayer.</p>
            <p>Theſe laſt words of <hi>David</hi> may be divided into theſe three heads: 1. His laſt Will and Advice to his Family. 2. His Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of his Infirmities, ſetting them up as Sea-marks or Buoys to prevent their Shipwrack. 3. His Profeſſion of a ſecur'd and aſſured Salvation, notwithſtanding theſe dangers, that he might engage them never to forſake their Fathers God, and their Fathers Covenant, that could ſuit and comfort a man toſſed among the Storms of Temptations, the Sands or Shelves of Sin, and Rocks of Death and Judgment.</p>
            <p>Firſt, His Advice to his Family, eſpecially his Sons, conſiſts in theſe three things, 1. Juſtice, <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>He that ruleth over men muſt be juſt.</hi> Honeſty is far before Honour; the latter is but an abuſe of the word without the former: The Lord forbids <hi>ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for great things</hi> in this World, but commands the <hi>providing of things honeſt in the ſight of all men.</hi> Injuſtice in ſuch a Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity would have the aggravation of vile degeneracy, it would be a diſowning of their Father, and preferring the Name of a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Baſtard before the Son of an Upright <hi>David.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Is Piety,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44461:4"/>
               <hi>ruling in the fear of God;</hi> this <hi>David</hi> enlarges his Commands about: 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Keep the charge of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. 1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 28.8. <hi>Keep and ſeek for all the Commandments of the Lord your God: Seek</hi> for them, what is of his appointment, and what not; and <hi>keep</hi> them, ſin not againſt Knowledge: <hi>Paul</hi> obtained Pardon, becauſe he <hi>did it ignorantly.</hi> Seek and keep <hi>all</hi> of them, thou obeyeſt none becauſe God has commanded if knowingly thou omit any: This is the too common ſin of Parents, to ſeparate Juſtice from Piety in the Education of their Children: If they be good Husbands, and Moral or Civil, they care for no more; but they will more and more find that a vain attempt to have their Children <hi>honeſt</hi> without <hi>Religion,</hi> both in the Root and Profeſſion of it, it is as impoſſible as to have a Picture without the Canvaſe it's drawn on, or a Shadow without the Subſtance, or a Bloſſom preſerved without the Root. 1. It is Worſhip and Religion that God has annexed his Promiſes to. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2.3. 1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 28.8. 2. It is to attempt the keeping of a part of an Indiviſible thing without the other, as if a Spiritual Being could be parted. 3. It is to attempt to preſerve the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Law without Motives, the Awe of God, Fear of his Wrath, or Love of his Goodneſs: We may ſee the ſucceſleſneſs of it in the Debauchery of the Age; ſince Religion and Profeſſion of it came in ſo much contempt, on that ground can we think God will take care of our Children, when we take no care of our Childrens fearing God? Do we think Children a fit ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject for Liberty of Conſcience? If they are, Baptiſmal Bonds are a moſt grievous Yoke impoſed on Parents, to train up Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the Knowledge of God, Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, and to bring them within the Bond of the Covenant with the bleſſed Trinity. A third Advice is about their Company, which is comprehended <hi>verſ.</hi> 6, 7. in ſhunning the Society of <hi>Belialites,</hi> ſuch men as <hi>Joab</hi> and <hi>Shimei</hi> it's like, for theſe are named, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 3. Two things are remarkable about them. 1. Who they are. 2. Why their Company ſo dangerous. (1.) The <hi>Belialites</hi> are men without Yoke, men of no Conſcience, no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, Atheiſts; they could be of any Profeſſion, that which was moſt for their Profit, or their Humour, but were really of no Principles, under no Law; if they took up any, it was as they do the Faſhion and Cuſtom of the Place they live in, for Company: A man had better be a Quaker, Papiſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44461:4"/>any Sect, rather than a <hi>Belialite,</hi> of no Religion; an atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal profane Crew, that can give no other Anſwer to any Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of Religion, about the Governour and Judge of the World, or their Souls Condition, than to grin like an Ape, as if their Reaſonable Souls by Debauchery were degenerate into Riſible ones. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſay, that <hi>Don Quixot</hi> has ruin'd the Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of <hi>Spain;</hi> and Sir <hi>William Temple</hi> who records it, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, <q>That we are like to exchange the Riches, the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Wſſdom of the Nation, for this Ridiculing Humour by Fools call'd <hi>Wit.</hi>
               </q> Never did theſe Vermin ſwarm thicker than at this day, (which makes with the former two Marks, <hi>viz.</hi> the Death of the Righteous, and Earthquakes in divers places, a Triple proof that the day of Judgment is at hand. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. Theſe are <hi>the Scoffers of the laſt days, ſaying, Where is the Promiſe of his coming?</hi>) (2.) Why their Company is ſo dangerous. 1. The Text ſays, becauſe of their Untractableneſs; they are as apt to hurt a man if he come in their Company, as Thorns to prick a man if he touch them; there is need of being fenc'd with Iron if he come nigh them, they wound ſo mortally; for a man muſt either comply with their Company, then his very Soul and Conſcience is wounded; or he muſt reſolutely oppoſe them, and then there muſt be War, Oppoſition, Quarrelling, Diſputing: If the former, he is a Proſelyte to the Brutal Herd, and an initiated Member of the Congregation of Evil-doers; if the latter, there is both need of Arms and Armour; and what man will frequent that Company where he muſt always be uneaſie, always contend, and be in danger of his Life? A Second Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, Becauſe their End is Deſtruction, <hi>They ſhall be utterly burnt with Fire.</hi> Who would walk with men that are going ſtrait to Hell? Who would live with men that have Ulcers of uncurable Plagues running upon them, when their Company is ſo infectious? May be it has prevail'd already ſo far on thee, that when out of their Company thou choofeſt not the ways of Life and Peace, and returns again to the ſame without the leaſt Antidote, what canſt thou look for but the Death of the Wicked that liv'ſt their Life? For as the Tree falls, ſo it will lye. O that Children who have diſobey'd the Commands of Parents when alive, would at leaſt let their laſt Will be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred with them: This <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerv'd long, though at laſt too much forgot it. How highly doth God commend the <hi>Rechabites,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44461:5"/>Jer.</hi> 35. for obeying their Fathers ſevere Commands, to drink no Wine, and to live in Tents? So highly diſpleaſed muſt he be with them, who diſobey moſt neceſſary and eaſie Precepts. The Text and the Time both, though not the Occaſion, where ſo much Love and Duty dwells, obliges me to this.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing is, the Acknowledgment of his Infirmities, <hi>Although my Houſe, —altho he make it not to grow:</hi> For the Matter of it, tho it's not an Auricular or particular Confeſſion, or in order to a Prieſtly Abſolution, yet from the Knowledge of his Life we may gueſs at the ground of his Grief. 1. <hi>David</hi> had much Guilt on his Conſcience; tho he was a <hi>man according to Gods Heart,</hi> yet his Perfection was not ſinleſneſs; he was not of the Quakers Principles, to boaſt of his Perfection; but did mourn over his Iniquities, though committed ſome Twenty, as his Murder of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> ſome Forty years before this. 2. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> had many Deſigns to fulfill, he wanted to reap the Comfort of his Labours, as to his own Houſe or the Houſe of God; he had conquer'd all his Enemies round about, and now he want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to enjoy a triumphant Peace, and plentifull poſſeſſion: He had <hi>Moſes</hi>-like brought the People to the borders of the Land of Reſt, but he muſt not go over to poſſeſs that beautiful Mountain of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> tho' he begg'd hard for it. He had with moſt induſtrious Pains, and incomparable Expences, prepar'd all Materials for the Houſe of God, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28. and God will not let him lay one Stone of the Houſe for all that. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.4. <hi>In that very day his thoughts periſh:</hi> All a mans Purpoſes, were they never ſo good or uſefull, periſh when the appointed Hour comes. 3. <hi>Davids</hi> Children were not ſo with God as he would have had them; there had been Inceſt, Murder and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion among them; and theſe who ſurviv'd, tho ſome of them lovely Children, and wiſer than their Father, and the root of the Matter in them too, <hi>Solomon</hi> the moſt wiſe, was belov'd of the Lord, and the Lord heard his Prayers again and again, yet that Zeal that the Old Man had for God was not in him. 4. <hi>Davids</hi> Grace did not grow, or <hi>bud</hi> and <hi>flouriſh,</hi> as the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal has it; he had Faith, but it did not flouriſh in the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Bloſſoms of Joy and Aſſurance, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.8, 12. <hi>The Joy of thy Salvation,</hi> that he wanted. The temporal Afflictions that the Godly meet with for their Backſidings, might be ſufficient Warnings and Motives to others, to walk more circumſpectly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44461:5"/>and Watchfully all their days. Here is an Intimation of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years Deſertion, and the Hour of Death fill'd up with the dreadful aſpect of Guilt. The Counſel of dying Perſons, about Religion, about Conſcience, about Duty and Sin, ought to be highly eſteemed; then they feel how evil and bitter a thing it is to ſin againſt God: If we ſee our righteous Fathers groaning over and ſmarting for their Infirmities on their Death-bed, what may we expect if we get our Souls for a Prey?</p>
            <p>The third Thing is, what was <hi>David</hi>'s Comfort under the ſenſe of approaching Death, thus arm'd with the Terrors of his own Guilt, and the Frowns of Heaven? It is certain no mean Cordials, no Temporary thing can ſupport his fainting Spirits then: Rooms full of Gold, the Company of all our Friends and Relations, the ſweeteſt Harmonies of Muſick, the daintieſt Diſhes, the ſtrongeſt Cordials, and moſt skill'd Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians; the only Helps a Man muſt betake himſelf to, are Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, for the Carkaſs periſhes. If a Man be not skill'd in Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and have ſome Spiritual Experiences, there is nothing that can bring any ſhadow of relief to him, but it is not every Divine either that can adminiſter to himſelf or others ſupport againſt Death, tho' that is the only Science that affords relief. Some expound the 3, 4, 5, <hi>Verſes,</hi> as ſo many different Topicks of relief to his Condition: 1. Experience, <hi>The Spirit of the Lord ſpoke by me:</hi> Shall God let me periſh, to whom he has given his Holy Spirit in ſuch a meaſure? But this might be baffl'd, God has taken his Spirit from thee, thou haſt ſinn'd away that Grace; a deſerted and tempted Soul is full of Error, and either may not believe the Doctrine of Perſeverance, or may miſtake the Graces of the Spirit for Gifts, ſuch as <hi>Balaam</hi> had. 2. The Nature of the Bleſſed Trinity, <hi>The God of Iſrael, the Rock of Iſrael, the Spirit of the Lord;</hi> the Attributes of God, the Mediatorial Offices of the Son, and ſweet Influences of the Spirit: But theſe may all become Thoughts of Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and Dread to a Soul, without ſome ſight of an Intereſt in them; as <hi>Peter, Depart from me, for I am a ſinful Man,</hi> and <hi>Adam</hi> when he heard God's Voice hid himſelf in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den: Therefore <hi>David,</hi> 3. Finally concludes on the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, as that thorough which the ſpiritual Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences were convey'd, and as that which contain'd the Terms of his Intereſt in God, its Properties and Articles, did obviate
<pb facs="tcp:44461:6"/>all Objections, the Diſeaſe could never be too ſtrong for its Balſams, nor the poyſon'd Arrows of Death could never drink up its comforting ſpirits: This affords the Doctrine I intend for the ſubject of the following Diſcourſe.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <label>Doct.</label> The Covenant of Grace is able to comfort all the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantees in it, againſt the Aſſaults of Death, arm'd with the moſt dreadful Stings that the Law, Sin, Satan, or Deſertion can afford to it.</p>
            </q>
            <p>This is the Honey we may eat out of the Carcaſe of this Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Juda;</hi> this is the rich Legacy left by his Will to all that are in Covenant with God; this is his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to all poor Sinners, as ever they would be ſafe at death, be ſure to be in Covenant with God. We have not this on his Experience only, he found it ſo at Death, nor on his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony only; the word of a King is too weak a Pillar to build the Salvation of our Immortal Souls upon; nor on the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony alone of the Spirit of God ſpeaking by him: But the ſame Spirit ſhows us the reaſon of the thing alſo, by ſetting down a Copy of this well-order'd Covenant, which I ſhall Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſe in theſe ſeven ſeveral Heads, that are ſo many Arguments to prove the Truth of this Doctrine: Its (1.) Divinity. (2.) Perſonality. (3.) Graciouſneſs. (4.) Everlaſtingneſs. (5.) Order. (6.) Sureneſs. (7.) Its Perfection, as to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Satisfaction. Having ſhewn from each of theſe apart, and much more from all put together, with how much ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction every Covenanted Soul may dye, whatever be the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections or blaſts upon the growth of their Grace, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever be the diſorder of the Affairs of their Houſe, whatever terrible uſe Satan may make of them, or ſorrow we may have from them, yet we may ſafely lay down our Corps in the Duſt, and bid Farewell to Sun, Moon and Stars, to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures below us, and our Friends about us, and ſay, Welcome Fellowſhip of Angels, Hail ever bleſſed Creator, Redeemer and Sanctifier; I come, I come, help me thorough this pain, guide me thorough this dark Valley of Death, diſpell this only remaining Cloud between me and that Sun of Righteouſneſs. I ſhall conclude with ſome uſefull Application, having proved and explained this Truth.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:44461:6"/>
            <p n="1">(1.) There is the <hi>Divinity</hi> of the Covenant, the more of God that there is in any thing, the more of Goodneſs there muſt be in it; for there is none good but God: God is 1. The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this Covenant, <hi>he hath made.</hi> The like expreſſion we find <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.3. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.31. Man that was but of Yeſterday, could never make an Everlaſting Covenant; Angels that are charg'd with folly, and are yet Students of its Myſteries, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12. could never bring things confounded by Sin into Order again; this Politick Union is founded on the Perſonal Union of <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel.</hi> Who could have contriv'd that? Who could have contriv'd a Righteouſneſs to anſwer the broken Law of the firſt Covenant? There are two moſt comforting Thoughts ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes from Gods being Author of the Covenant, the Goodneſs of the end, and wiſe contrivance of the Means: 1. The Goodneſs of the End; Perſons that have any Grains of Honeſty left, when they enter a Confederacy with others, deſign a mutual Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. It is a meer Cheat to draw Perſons into a Commerce, or Policy they can get no good, but hurt by. But God can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive no Good, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 16. <hi>Our goodneſs extends not to him;</hi> and his Glory conſiſts in giving, that we may ſee there is ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exhauſtible Fountain of Goodneſs and Bleſſedneſs in him, that when Sinners have receiv'd a full Salvation, Guilt a compleat Pardon, and all empty deſire a full ſatisfaction meaſur'd out by Wiſdom, ſo that it may not ſatiate, but ſtill preſerve ſo far the Deſire, as to delight in receiving; all the advantage muſt be ours: If any part of this Deſign ſhould fail of making us compleatly happy, it would reflect on Divine Alſufficiency, it would eclipſe his Glory. We are made Sons by Covenant, and will a Father ſee his Children ſtarve while he poſſeſſes any thing? 2. The wiſe Contrivance of the Means; there is not one Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the Covenant that we would deſire left out, or one Article we could deſire added to it, if our Underſtandings were come to a mature perfection to judge of ſuch a Concern, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22. <hi>Death is ours,</hi> we would rather want it; but how ſhall we get to Heaven without Death, for <hi>Fleſh and Blood</hi> cannot enterit? Or how ſhall this Earth be chang'd into a glorious Condition without Death? There are many more Reaſons we know not; all <hi>things preſent are ours:</hi> We would rather want many of our preſent. Conditions and Circumſtances, Sickneſs, Poverty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but (<hi>Rom.</hi> 8.) all theſe work together for our good: If this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:44461:7"/>Covenant ſhould any way fail or prove deficient, we may bleſs God we had no hand in it; or rather that all in it was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived by him, all its Clauſes, Terms and Articles, were ſettled and Authoritatively publiſh'd before we knew one Word of it; if it come ſhort of its End, it will not be thorough our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault, he knew what we were when he Contriv'd the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for our Happineſs, he enter'd into Covenant with us as Sinners, it will reflect on his Wiſdom and Circumſpection, his Foreſight or Prudence. <hi>Obj.</hi> The firſt Covenant fail'd of its End, and that was made by God. <hi>Reſp.</hi> It's poſitively falſe, for it was Contriv'd, and that Primitive Conſtitution of Man too, as a Means to bring in the Covenant of Grace and the Happineſs of Man thorough it. Man's Bleſſedneſs was not the immediate End of that Covenant. To ſay God is come ſhort of his End, fruſtrated and diſappointed, is to make him not God. The learned <hi>Strangius</hi> ſays, tho' Sin is no means of God's Glory, Permiſſion of ſin was, for that made way for Creatures being brought from a low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Condition, and greater diſtance from God than meer nothing was; by it the ſteps of nigh infinite ſucceſſions and degrees of Happineſs are increas'd; Goodneſs bloſſoms into Grace and Mercy, by making an Inhabitant of Hell, whether by Act or Deſert, an Heir and Poſſeſſor of Heaven; but it had remained a meer Goodneſs that it had made a Clod of Clay an Angel: What a Manifeſtation of Infiniteneſs, for Creatures to be always increaſing, but ever ſhort of God's fulneſs!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Divinity of the Covenant appears in God's being the Party as well as the Author, <hi>Zach.</hi> 13 ch. <hi>laſt</hi> Ver. <hi>I will ſay it is my People, and they ſhall ſay the Lord is my God,</hi> and that diſtinctly in all the Relatives of the Bleſſed Trinity. We enter into Covenant with God as Father; Chriſt ſays, <hi>I go to your Father and my Father:</hi> We enter Covenant with God as Son in all his Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torial Offices: We enter into Covenant with the Holy Ghoſt in all his ſanctifying and glorifying Influences: We ſee <hi>David</hi> here ſet all the Bleſſed Trinity, <hi>the God of Iſrael, the Rock of Iſrael, and the Spirit of the Lord,</hi> before the Covenant, as the Perſons he did indent with. And it is yet more diſtinctly ſet down in the Baptiſmal Form of the Covenant, in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt: This helps to remove ſome Difficulties about the Covenants Conditionality; for the whole Law being in its Nature as unchangeable as the Relations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:44461:7"/>the Creator and Creature, it ſtands ſtill the Meaſure and Standard of Duties and Conditions of the Covenant of Grace; but what Conditions the Father as Fountain of Authority requires, the Son as Mediator, Surety, and Cautioner performs, and what this Mediator as God's Vicegerent and Deputy requires, the Spirit enables us to do, whoſe Operations are both preventive and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual; ſo this Covenant of Grace is an abſolute Diſpoſition of Grace notwithſtanding all the Laws and Duties of it; for there are no preparative Duties required in order to the Spirits Influences, nor may be no Perſons in this World without ſome of his Beams and Rayes; for as it is Chriſt's Merits that preſerves this Earth from being a Hell, ſo it is the Spirits Influences that keeps the Temper of Man in any better Condition than that of Devils. There is a vaſt difference between what Man actually is, and what he is <hi>De jure,</hi> by Nature: We are Children of Wrath by Nature, our Underſtanding is meer Darkneſs, and our Wills a meer Enmity: We would ſin deſignedly againſt God, and deſignedly Diſhonour him; We would intend Rebellion in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry act, and this ſeems to be the Apoſtles Intention, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. <hi>There hath no Temptation taken you but ſuch as is common to Man;</hi> to ſin at this rate is not common to Man, Man's Deſign is not higher than his own Profit or his Pleaſure, the Proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of which though he knows it is a Sin, yet he wiſhes it were not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Divinity of this Covenant appears in God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, his Attributes, Perſonalities and Providential Operations, being all the Promiſed Bleſſings of the Covenant; for the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is a Marriage Covenant, wherein not as in other Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants of Peace or War, Trade or Commerce, the Obligation is limited to ſome particular thing, here the Party and all he hath comes under Obligation: Hence is that Argument good, Becauſe he lives we ſhall live alſo; and Chriſt's Proof for the Reſurrection of the Body and Immortality of the Soul, that <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> are alive, becauſe God is the God of the Living. Nothing can utterly dye that is in this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, becauſe God's Life is engaged to keep them alive. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed this exceeds Marriage Contracts, becauſe the Husband hath not a Life to communicate, nor a Power to preſerve his own. God's Omnipotency is ours; <hi>I am the Almighty, walk be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me and be thou perfect.</hi> We need not fear the Power of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44461:8"/>Enemies, his Immutabillity, <hi>I Change not, therefore ye ſhall not be be conſumed:</hi> And all his Creatures, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22. <hi>The World, Life, Death, things preſent, or things to come, all are yours:</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidential Operations, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. <hi>For we know that all things work together for good to them that love God:</hi> Pſal. 25.10. <hi>All his ways are mercy and truth to ſuch as keep his Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) There is the <hi>Perſonality</hi> of the Covenant, <hi>Thou haſt made with me:</hi> Though God entered into Covenant with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> for himſelf and his Seed, yet as ſoon as his Seed did exiſt in the World, he did perſonally enter into Covenant with them, firſt with <hi>Iſaac</hi> and then with <hi>Jacob;</hi> and the more Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous we find any Perſons in Scripture, the more frequent we find them in this Exerciſe: <hi>David</hi>'s firſt <hi>Michtam</hi> or Golden Pſalm, begins thus, <hi>O my Soul, thou haſt ſaid unto the Lord, Thou art my Lord,</hi> with his Expectation of the like Anſwer from God, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 35.3. <hi>Say unto my Soul, I am thy Salvation:</hi> God's Language is Providential, ſo that it's to the ſame purpoſe, when he ſays, <hi>Preſerve me O God, for in thee do I put my truſt.</hi> Our Faith is our Perſonal Covenanting, and God's preſerving is his Virtual Saying, He will be <hi>Our Saviour,</hi> this is Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyed to be more frequent and more formal under the New Teſtament State than it was under the Old, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 44.5. <hi>One ſhall ſay I am the Lords, and another ſhall call himſelf by the Name of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and another ſhall ſubſcribe with his hand unto the Lord:</hi> Iſaiah 45.24. <hi>Surely ſhall men ſay, in the Lord have I righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſtrength:</hi> The Apoſtle doth moſt pathetically preſs this Perſonal Dedication, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1. <hi>I beſeech you therefore Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, by the mercies of God, ye preſent your Bodies a living Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, holy, acceptable unto God, which is your reaſonable ſervice:</hi> And the Practice of the Primitive Church anſwer'd their Apoſtolical Advice, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5. <hi>They firſt gave themſelves to the Lord, and to us by the Will of the Lord:</hi> The different Conſtitution of the Viſible Church under the New Teſtament, from that under the Old, and the different Adminiſtration of the Covenant, have a conſiderable Influence to make the formal performance of this more our Duty; for it is in part upon this Account that the Church is called (<hi>Mat.</hi> 16.) a Church <hi>de futuro, I will build my Church,</hi> as <hi>Camero</hi> obſerves: It was a Building to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, whereof the Foundations were not yet laid, and the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant a new Covenant. Firſt, For the Conſtitution of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:44461:8"/>Church, we have a fair Account of it in the 18th. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> in Chriſt's Anſwer to the Diſciples Queſtion about the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven: <hi>Firſt,</hi> There is the Qualifications of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, <hi>Verſe</hi> 3. <hi>Converted ones, become as little Children. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> Their formal Entrance into the Kingdom of Chriſt, and their Reception in the Name of Chriſt by them that are in it, <hi>Verſe</hi> 5. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> There is an account of the great Evil that doth any ways hinder or hurt this Conſtitution, or theſe little Ones now received into it, and therefore becomes the only Object of Church-Diſcipline that is Offence. Sin is only againſt God's immediate Government, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. <hi>Againſt thee, thee only, have I ſinned:</hi> He only can Forgive it, he only can Puniſh it: It is a Breach of his Law only, Offence is againſt the Church, as being that which occaſions any Member thereof to ſin, or by which its Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers may offend others; but ſcarce any can Offend but them that are in the Church. Injuries which hurt a Man's Body or Eſtate, are the Objects of the Civil Government: One Act may have all the three Evils in it, and may be Puniſhed by all the three Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> There are the remedying Rules or Methods of Diſcipline about this Evil, ſet down <hi>Verſe</hi> 15, 16, 17. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> There is the ſupream Court, where the laſt Appeal lyes in Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of this Affair, with the laſt and moſt ſevere Puniſhment this Court can Inflict: The former is the Church, the latter is an Excluſion from that Society, for then he can Offend no more; as a Dead Man in the State can injure no more. The laſt thing is, the way of the Conſtitution of this Court, and the Reaſon why we ought to acquieſce in its Judgment about ſuch Affairs: The former is the ſtated and agreed Meeting of ſuch Converts in the Name of Chriſt, the latter is from Chriſt's being among them, his Promiſe to hear them, his Inſtitution of them, and Conſerring Authority to the Ordinance; now this Agreement <hi>to continue ſtedfaſtly in the Apoſtles Doctrine, in mutual Fellowſhip, in breaking of Bread and in Prayer,</hi> Acts 2.42. doth formally Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute a Covenant; it is a Fulfillment of that Prophecy, <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.5. <hi>Come, and let us join our ſelves unto the Lord;</hi> and it doth ſuppoſe their Perſonal Covenanting with God, for they who come into it are to be received as little Children, and as Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted ones; and tho' Perſons cannot give account when they were firſt Converted, more than when they were firſt Conceived or Born, without their Parents Information, yet they may give
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:44461:9"/>Account of their Perſonal Covenanting with God, and when it was, tho' with great difference in Explicitneſs or Implicitneſs, in the bare Exerciſe of Faith and Prayer, and the ſecret Thoughts of the Hearts, or in external Words or Writing
<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Mr.</hi> Baxter, <hi>on Confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the way to Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</hi>
               </note>. <hi>Secondly,</hi> In the New Adminiſtration of the Covenant, which receives its Alteration very much from the New Conſtitution of the Church; for in the former all Circumciſed were in the Church, here it's only thoſe that are Converted; ſo all <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Natural Seed through <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> were within the Covenant, as to all its viſible Priviledges, but in this New Adminiſtration they are brought under the Covenant, by the Lord's pouring out his Spirit on them, by his putting his Laws in their Minds, and writing them on their Hearts, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. The very Import of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Law in the Mind, is a willing and ready Compliance with them known, a being made willing in the day of his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, a hearty undertaking to perform them, followed with ſome ſuitable Endeavours, and what is this elſe but perſonal Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting?</p>
            <p>Our ſatisfying our ſelves with a Virtual Performance of this is too common and too groſs a defect to be indulged, that is, a complyance with the Duties of the Covenant in ſome meaſure, without a ſerious ſetting about this Duty firſt, and entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it; this is doing Violence to the Beauty and Order of this well ordered Covenant, which requires our In-being before our Doing, or our Receiving. <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is an Omiſſion of a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive enjoyned Duty. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is very unbecoming God's tranſacting with us, who has formerly drawn up the Covenant in all its Articles, and has ſet his Name to it, and has record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it in his Word, and has appointed a vaſt Number of Men under the Office of the Miniſtry to Publiſh it, and has furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them with the Spirit to Interpret and Inculcate it, and their great Meſſage is, <q>Be ye reconciled to God, be at Peace with him, enter into Covenant with him, and faithfully keep and obſerve it:</q> Is this a ſuitable Correſpondence to God's Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action, that we wo'nt come under Obligation, but we will do as we find Opportunity and have Occaſion or Convenience, as it may conſiſt with our other Intereſts and Concerns? This is in effect to ſay, we will not at all; for the Covenant requires that we be wholly God's, utterly denying our ſelves and all our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, as he hath given himſelf wholly to us. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:44461:9"/>Manner of Perſons entring into Covenant with Sathan, who is God's Ape, and who hath ſet up a Kingdom and a Covenant in direct Oppoſition to our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, may have ſome Influence both for Illuſtrating and Inculcating this Duty, which the Learned <hi>Weems</hi> thus explains: <q>Sathan doth all he can to perſwade his Subjects formally to Covenant with him, to put one Hand under their Foot, and another above their Head, and give all between them to Sathan, or to write a Bond of Reſignation of themſelves, and Seal it with their Blood; and if they be Baptized Chriſtians, that they formally Renounce their Baptiſm; but if he cannot attain theſe things, he has a ſet of Ordinances made up of Charms and unreaſonable Arts, as Aſtrology, Chiromancy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which he in his way Bleſſeth with Succeſs as far as he can, thoſe who follow the Practice of them.</q> This is a Virtual Covenanting with him. Now as we would not Judge all ſuch Witches or Wizards who do too frequently Practiſe Charms, either in Cures, Progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks or Injuries, ſo we ought not to think all true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans who perform Chriſtian Ordinances: And if Covenanting with Sathan has ſuch a Power to make us his, that but very few are recovered from Hell who go to ſuch a heighth in ſinning, what an Influence muſt Perſonal Covenanting with God have to make us his, when there is ſo great difference in Contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for we are gull'd and deceived in the one: It is in great Ignorance we Covenant with Sathan. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Sathan deceives us, and never fulfills the half of what he Promiſes. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> God has an antecedent Right, and therefore our Covenanting with Sathan is Unlawful. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> God has a greater Power, and he hath ſent Chriſt on that very Office, to deſtroy the Works of the Devil, therefore there is a Poſſibility of Recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry out of that State, but no final Relapſe from the other; for <hi>No man can pluck the Sheep out of the Father's hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> The Diſcouragements that hinder Perſons from ſuch a ſacred Engagement, are more from Ignorance of them, than reality in the things themſelves. As firſt, Some are frighted by the greatneſs of the Obligation, and their Inability to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form: To which I anſwer, We are under all that Obligation already, it rather relieves than oppreſſes. Chriſt ſays his <hi>Burthen is light,</hi> and his <hi>Yoke eaſie;</hi> it is no more Burthen than Wings to a Bird; for the Apoſtle ſays, He that is not <hi>under the Law
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:44461:10"/>is under Grace;</hi> and <hi>what things the Law ſays,</hi> it is <hi>to them that are under the Law.</hi> There is no Duty thou engageſt to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, but thou waſt obliged as a Creature to perform before, and by this Covenanting thou getſt a Right and Intereſt in Chriſt, by which all thy paſt Diſobedience is pardoned, the burden of Guilt taken off, and thou receiveſt ſtrength to obey better for the future: For the Providential Language of God in Covenanting with a Soul, is the giving of his Spirit; hence this is the Language of one that underſtandingly enters into Covenant with God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.24. <hi>Surely to him ſhall men come,</hi> ſaying, <hi>In the Lord have I righteouſneſs and ſtrength.</hi> A ſecond Diſcouragement is, from the ſenſe of Deſertion, and want of the Spirit; from perſons own unfitneſs and unholineſs, they ſay with <hi>Peter, Depart from me, for I am a ſinful man. Reſp.</hi> This is from a Miſtake about the end of the Law; the Lord bleſſes the Law, or ſends his Spirit to impower it, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. when the Spirit convinces of Sin; ſo the end of this is to drive us to Chriſt, to make us ſeek a ſhelter under Grace, when we are ſcorched with the heat of the fiery Law: Hence Chriſt calls, <hi>Come unto me all ye that are weary and heavy laden.</hi> Secondly, How diſorderly would we have God to act toward us, to ſay, If he will fill us with Comfort and Joy, and give us Aſſurance, the very top Bleſſings of the Covenant in this Life, or rather the Earneſt and Beginnings of the other Life, if he will fulfill all the Covenant to me, then will I enter Covenant with him. A third is from the fear of Hypocritical acting with God, and ſo rather ſin and provoke him to deſtroy me, than to receive me into this State of Salvation. <hi>Reſp.</hi> I know no better Cure of Hypocriſie, than to bring and keep the Heart in the View of God, and under the Awe of his Preſence: In the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Luke,</hi> we ſee this wrought a conſiderable Cure upon a <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee,</hi> tho' the greateſt Hypocrites in the World. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 11. <hi>God I thank thee that I am not as other men:</hi> He did not ſpeak ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to his own Principles, to own God the Author of that difference that was between him and any other Man in Matter of Religion: It was the Awe of God upon Conſcience that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted the Truth out of it; and I have heard Free-willers pray as inconſiſtently with their own Profeſſion, which made me have far more Charity to their Perſons than their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. But (2.) Thy Condition is like the Lepers at the gate
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:44461:10"/>of <hi>Samaria,</hi> thou art ſure to ſtarve if out of Covenant, and art ſure to ſin againſt God out of Covenant in every thing thou doſt; but thou haſt a <hi>May-be</hi> for it, if thou fly to this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, and lay hold of the Covenant; and doſt not thou think that if God ſpoke immediately from Heaven to thee, in a time of Plague, Famine, Sword or Sickneſs, and ſay, May be thou ſhalt be ſafe in ſuch a Place, that thou wouldſt ſpeedily fly to ſuch an <hi>Aſylum?</hi> But we have more encouragement, the King already holding out the Scepter, and declaring his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs to accept Imperfect Performance, that we may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach with greater Courage than an <hi>Eſther</hi> before her <hi>Aha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuerus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> It is ſuch an Encouragement at Death, when all other Comforts prove as broken Ciſterns without Water, <hi>Thou haſt made with me a Covenant,</hi> is a Shete-Anchor of Hope; and ſo much the more when they have had the Verdict of a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of grave, ſerious and experienc'd Chriſtians, that their Covenanting was not formal and hypocritical, but ſincere and accepted of God; that the temper of Mind it was performed with, could be the Effect of no leſs Author than the Spirit of God, the Birth beſpoke its Father to be Heavenly, when each of that Company of ſagacious Saints witneſs'd that it was on the ſame Bottom their Hopes were built, and that their Souls were all in a like Condition, in the ſame Bundle of Life; and this not without a Miniſter of the Word holding that Glaſs before their Face, wherein they might ſee their Language to be a Copy of that Original, and that this Harveſt was from the Seed of the Word. This has prov'd to many the ſweeteſt and ſtrongeſt Cordial they had at Death, and there is ground to judge the Conſolation ſolid, ſince <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. Chriſt has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd what they <hi>looſe on Earth,</hi> he would <hi>in Heaven;</hi> what they <hi>agreed about to ask,</hi> he would <hi>grant;</hi> and ſuch a Verdict is not paſs'd without ſerious Prayer to God in the Name of Chriſt, for a Judgment of Diſcerning in that preſent affair. Is this the thing that diſcourages People from Joyning unto Churches of ſuch a Conſtitution, that becomes ſo much mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Comfort and Encouragement at the hour of Death? Who that are ſeriouſly concern'd about their own Salvation, would want ſuch an Ordinance of Tryal? I think it is the Reverend Mr. <hi>Ba.</hi> who adviſes Perſons to write the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:44461:11"/>of their Soul, and deſire ſome Miniſters or underſtanding Chriſtians Verdict of it: But I think this Verdict is preferable on ſeveral Accompts. 1. As much as the Verdict of many is before the Judgment of one, or a Church before a ſingle perſon's. 2. As much as a Divine Ordinance that has ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the Spirits Conduct, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. before a humane Help and Expedient. That which indeed firſt recommended it to me, was a Gentlewoman on her Death-bed, who bewail'd <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>-like her want of growth much, and had this complex Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence alone left, which ſhe improved much more pathetically than I have here expreſs'd it: I have found it the Experience of three more ſince in the like condition, tho not under ſuch backſliding or deſertion.</p>
            <p>The Third Property is, the <hi>Graciouſneſs</hi> of the Covenant: The word <hi>gracious</hi> is not in the Text, nor is it any where in Scripture verbally the Epithet of this Covenant, tho moſt uſual among Divines; and there is reaſon enough for it, for a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant cannot be made between the Creator and Creature with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a gracious condeſcendency; and therefore ſome will not allow the Law of Works to bear the Name of a Covenant, becauſe there cannot be a Covenant and not of Grace. Perſons that have a Deſpotick Power, as a Maſter over a Slave, or a Father over a Child, will not enter into Terms with them: The end of a Covenant is to bring Perſons under Obligation that are free; and therefore Kings love not to hear of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant terms between them and their People. Now Gods ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent Right being Soveraign, and abſolutely founded on Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it's rather a giving away his Right than getting one: <hi>Thy Maker is thy Husband,</hi> contains a Miracle of Grace in it. 2. Its being a Teſtament, this famous Name gives Title to all the Bible, the Old and New Teſtament. This is the Nature of a Teſtament, it can Convey nothing but what is good, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges but no Puniſhments: All things that are Convey'd are Tokens, Legacies, Eſtate or Inheritance; if any hard Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be annexed, the Perſon is not Obliged to accept; ſo muſt be gracious by its being a Teſtament, but how much more if we conſider it as ſumm'd up by Chriſt, from <hi>John</hi> 12. to 18. <hi>ch.</hi> He leaves the Father our Tutor and Guardian, the Holy Ghoſt Executor, Heaven as an Inheritance, Meaſures of Grace as Legacies, Joy and Peace as Love-Tokens; he leaves us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:44461:11"/>the Notion of Babes, that cannot Forfeit their Eſtate with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their Executor and Guardians conſent, which is impoſſible; therefore in this ſence true, <hi>He that is born of God cannot ſin.</hi> 3. It's gracious, becauſe ſo full of Promiſes; <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.6.17. it's call'd a <hi>Command</hi> and a <hi>Law</hi> too, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 111.10. <hi>who hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his Covenant for ever;</hi> becauſe all the <hi>Law,</hi> that is <hi>holy, juſt and good,</hi> is ſtill required in it, being unchangeable in their Nature; but now Grace ſhines in their being put in this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, where Grace is promiſed to enable and ſtrengthen us to obey: We are under all the Law, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. Chriſt came not to deſtroy it; and our Condition enlarges the Duties of the Law, mixes Humility with Sorrow, Obedience with Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; and ſo the new Diſcoveries of God by the Goſpel en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larges the Objects of Faith. <hi>Ye believe in God, belive alſo in me:</hi> And our Obligation is greater, as a Married Woman is more obliged to Chaſtity than a Virgin, and <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Nurſe more obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged than another Nurſe, becauſe alſo a Mother. But there is ſo much Grace in the Promiſes that overballances all this. 1. The mixing or joining of Chriſt's Works with ours, the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace and Redemption together, ſupply the Place of the broken Covenant of Works: Hence our Imperfect Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence if in Faith is accepted for perfect, the Will for the Deed. <hi>Nathan</hi> ſays to <hi>David, Becauſe it was in thine Heart to build to me a Houſe, I will build to thee a ſure Houſe;</hi> it admits of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to ſupply the Place of Obedience, it gives ſtrength to Obey, this Uniting of the Command and the Promiſe makes it appear Conditional, but the Certainty and Ability to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Conditions, both depending upon the Promiſes, takes away the proper Nature of a Condition, (whoſe Properties are, 1. <hi>Poteſtative,</hi> in the Perſon's Power to perform them. 2. <hi>Caſualis,</hi> the other Party being uncertain whether we would Perform them or not. 3. <hi>Cauſalis,</hi> in reſpect of Right, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſome Valuable Conſiderations) and leaves a bare Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Connexion or Ordered Covenant, inſtead of a Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Covenant; and the many <hi>Ifs</hi> uſed in Scripture to be the <hi>Ifs</hi> of Demonſtration uſed by Civilians in Teſtaments, or Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians in Arguing; not the <hi>If</hi> of a proper Condition, tho' it's uſual among Divines and Proteſtants to uſe it for Priority of Order, and that is not inconſiſtent with Graciouſneſs.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:44461:12"/>
            <p>But I need not ſqueeze this Covenant ſo to bring Graciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs out of it by ſuch Inferences, when <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.14. the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is ſaid to be <hi>of Grace,</hi> the Covenant call'd <hi>a Covenant of Peace,</hi> and its Bleſſings <hi>ſure Mercies;</hi> when all the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantees are Sinners, Rebels, when the greateſt of them are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Choſen, and that like <hi>Manaſſe,</hi> in the Heighth of their Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and when all their Sins are forgiven at once, when the firſt Condition or Duty of the Covenant is meer Faith, a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, and when to do that is the Work of the Spirit, both as to firſt and laſt of it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. <hi>The Author and Finiſher of our Faith:</hi> Eph. 2.8. <hi>It is the Gift of God:</hi> And ſo long as one Spark of Life remains in that Appetite fixed or determined on God, our right in the Covenant ſtands: <hi>I believe, Lord help my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief: Faith as a Grain of Muſtard-ſeed:</hi> And tho' it ſhou'd loſe ſight of many of its Objects, it ought to be receiving and truſting God for, <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief of Man will not render the Faith of God of none effect.</hi> We may ſing, <hi>Grace, Grace,</hi> to every Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of this Covenant, and what can ſupport a Man in ſight of Death if Grace will not? A Man cannot diſcern himſelf in a Covenant of Grace and not ſee God on a Throne of Grace, and when a Soul apprehends God as gracious, it apprehends him as 1. Good, for that is the ground-work. 2. As Love, for that's the Spring. 3. As Merciful, for the Object's miſerable. 4. As Sovereign, Free and Abſolute, in diſpenſing of Bleſſings and Benefits, for to ſhew Grace is abſolute Monarchy: Hence all the Acts of Government are for Exalting this Throne, to <hi>the Praiſe of the Glory of his Grace,</hi> Eph. 1. I ſee my Guilt, but I ſee Pardoning Grace; I feel ſin, but I feel reſtraining and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing Grace; I ſee Death, but I ſee over-ordering Grace: This ſupports the Soul.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Fourth</hi> Property is the <hi>Everlaſtingneſs</hi> of the Covenant: <hi>Thou haſt made with me an Everlaſting Covenant,</hi> Pſal. 103.17. <hi>The Mercy of the Lord is from everlaſting to everlaſting,</hi> Iſa. 55.3. The ſure Mercies of <hi>David</hi> are called an <hi>Everlaſting Covenant.</hi> The Covenant of Works was before the Covenant of Grace in Time, and in Order of Execution, as all Means are before their End, but the Covenant of Grace was before it in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Intention. Grace could not have been ſo branched forth in Mercy and Forgiveneſs, if the former had not been both made and broken: On this Account this Covenant of Grace was
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:44461:12"/>from Everlaſting, being founded on Everlaſting Love; <hi>With an Everlaſting Love have I loved thee, therefore with Loving-kindneſs will I draw thee:</hi> It is founded on the everlaſting Thoughts that did emanate from that Love, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.5. The thoughts that <hi>were ever of Old,</hi> they are <hi>more than can be numbred,</hi> and on the <hi>everlaſting Purpoſes</hi> that thoſe Thoughts did reſult in, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. <hi>According to his Grace and Purpoſe which was given us in Chriſt before the World began:</hi> And as it was from Everlaſting, ſo it is unto Everlaſting: A Perſon once brought into it, ſhall always remain in it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.33. <hi>If they break my Statutes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>then will I viſit their Tranſgreſſions with the Rod,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>nevertheleſs my Loving-kindneſs will I not utterly take from them.</hi> There is a threefold ground of this Perſeverance. 1. Becauſe of God's engaging his own Fidelity, he will not <hi>ſuffer his faithfulneſs to fail;</hi> the Unbelief of Men will not render the Faith of God of none effect. 2. His Promiſe unto Chriſt: <hi>Once have I ſworn to David, that his Seed ſhould endure for ever.</hi> 3. The Promiſe of perſevering and ſecuring Grace; he will <hi>put his Fear in their Hearts,</hi> that <hi>they ſhall not depart from him.</hi> The Confederating Parties, the Ever-living God and Immortal Souls are Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and this Relation between them ſhall never be altered; this is the Reaſon of Chriſt's proving of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi>'s being yet alive, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.32. from God's being their Covenanted God, <hi>I am the God of Abraham, the God of Iſaac, and the God of Jacob; God is not the God of the dead, but of the living.</hi> Pſal. 24.7. The Faculties of our Soul under the Figure of <hi>Doors</hi> or <hi>Gates</hi> are called <hi>everlaſting,</hi> for they are ſo many Capacities or Deſires for ſeeking after, receiving and enjoying of that <hi>King of Glory:</hi> Hence is that explicatory <hi>Verſe</hi> 5, 6. <hi>This is the Generation of them that ſeek him,</hi> that receive <hi>the Bleſſing from the Lord, and righteouſneſs from the God of his Salvation:</hi> There is an <hi>everlaſting</hi> God, and an <hi>everlaſting</hi> Soul, an <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting</hi> Appetite, and an <hi>everlaſting</hi> Satisfying that the Commerce among the Inhabitants of the holy Hill of the Lord conſiſts in, and this Covenant of Grace contains the Municipal Laws of that Traffick. This is another Pillar that renders the Covenant of ſuch a ſupporting Nature, eſpecially at Death, for that cannot break an everlaſting Tye; tho we dye to this World, and all the Relations founded by other Covenants, whether Marriage, Peace, War, Friendſhip, Death is the Death of all
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:44461:13"/>of them, but it makes not the leaſt breach upon this. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38. <hi>I am perſwaded that neither Death, nor Life, ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the Love of God.</hi> We are ſtill alive to God, and muſt receive the Promiſes ſuitable to that ſeparate State between Soul and Body, and muſt perform the Duties proper to it, whereof we know nothing ſo much as the God in that Covenant Relation we go to, which contains Comfort enough againſt the loſs of all the Relatives we part with.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Fifth</hi> Property is its Harmonious Order, and the greateſt Controverſies among Proteſtants are about this; the different Methods and Syſtems of Divinity, are ſo many different Orders they conceive divine Wiſdom to have fram'd the Covenant in: And no wonder we miſtake in attempting to fathom the depth of divine Myſteries, untill the Eyes of our Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be enlightned with Viſion, and we admitted to read the Divine Records in their Original in Heaven. We but know in part, and no man that knows but a part of a Book only, can give a true Analyſis of it; for every new Notion that we attain, alters ſomewhat of our former Method: This Order is called <hi>the Form of ſound Words,</hi> the <hi>Form of Godlineſs.</hi> Order is a Diſpoſition of things according to their natural or uſeful Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority or Poſteriority; the former holds in Speculatives, the latter in Practicals.</p>
            <p>There are three things in the Covenant, whoſe Order is prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally to be obſerved: The Subjects, the Matter, the Ends.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) As to the Subjects, I ſhall but name them. <hi>Firſt,</hi> God is concern'd about the Covenant before us, he made it. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> That the Order of the Trinity is obſervable in it. 1. It flows from the Love of the Father, and is contrived by his Wiſdom. 2. The Bleſſings of it purchaſed, or way for the Execution of the Contrivance, that it might conſiſt with the Juſtice of Divine Government, made by the Son. 3. The Execution of it is by the Spirit. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That Chriſt as our Mediator and Head was in Covenant for us before us; as the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was in the firſt Covenant before us, ſo the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> was; hence we receive all thorough him. Eph. 1. <hi>He hath bleſs'd us with all ſpiritual Bleſſings in Chriſt Jeſus. He ſhall take of mine, and give it unto you.</hi> We eat his Fleſh, and drink his Blood; we receive our Meaſures from that Immenſe ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs treaſur'd up in him: There was no new Covenant to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervene
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:44461:13"/>between the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> and his Seed, in order to their partaking of the Priviledges promiſed to him, or poſſeſs'd by him. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Perſons muſt firſt be in Covenant before they partake of its Priviledges; Subjects muſt precede their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties; all the Promiſes of the Bible, <hi>blotting out Sins and Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities,</hi> cannot ſolidly comfort thee who art not in Covenant; only thus far, I may be in Covenant, and then they are mine: The Man muſt be firſt taken, before any Right to what he has; this is the one thing neceſſary to poor Sinners, that they be in Covenant once. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> There is a great difference, tho not in Right, yet in Priority of Order, as to Poſſeſſion among the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of this Covenant. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.23. <hi>Every one in their own Order.</hi> Iſa. 9. <hi>Of the Increaſe of his Government there</hi> will <hi>be no end;</hi> and that Increaſe by Order: There are Variety of Forms and Claſſes in Chriſts School, the Loweſt is in this World, which is but a meer Initiation into it. The greateſt Bleſſings here bear the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Titles or Earneſts of the Future, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.17. tho ſo big as to enable us to live, to maintain and propare us. By vertue of this Order Sinleſneſs is as neceſſary a Condition of our entring Heaven, as Faith is of our Pardon or Juſtification.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) There is the Order of the Matter of the Covenant, which conſiſts in the Promiſes and Precepts of it, abſtractly or in their mutual Aſpect. 1. Abſtractly, with reſpect to the Promiſes of the Covenant, there is an Order among them; there are ſome Promiſes whoſe fulfillment we may expect and do enjoy in this Life, ſome not; as that no Temptation ſhall befall us that ſhall totally conquer us in this Life; but a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in Knowledge and Holineſs, a doing away of what is in part, a being without Spot or wrinkle, are Bleſſings pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the future Life; a being freed from all Suffering, is proper to the other Life, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.9. There is no Promiſe but what beiongs to the Covenant, nor no Bleſſing but what comes thro' the Promiſes. 2. There are ſome Promiſes <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute,</hi> others <hi>conditional.</hi> God gives a Stock before he requires any Improvement; God required no Duty untill he had made a Creature, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tted it with Faculties for performing of the Duties he required, nor doth now the Covenant of Grace, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Law ſtill keep up its Right, and claim the exerciſe of Faith, one of the firſt duties of the Covenant, but the Gift of Faith is before it: The Promiſe of the Redeeming Seed,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:44461:14"/>
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. was preventive of all Duties; there was need of believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, in order to all ſaving Bleſſings by it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. but the Nature of that Faith was ſuch, as no external Revelation or Motives could alone bring forth. A clear Diſcovery, <hi>ver.</hi> 1. of <hi>inviſible things</hi> realized to the Mind, the Idea of them form'd in the Soul; for <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. <hi>darkneſs</hi> could not <hi>comprehend the Light,</hi> and the <hi>natural Man knoweth not the things of God.</hi> 3. Legal Promiſes are before Evangelical; <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. the Spirit <hi>convinces of Sin</hi> before it <hi>convince of Righteouſneſs,</hi> though there be great difference between the degrees of Conviction and Humiliation ſome are under; yet no man will ever fly to a Refuge, that is not ſenſible of need; no man will truſt to anothers Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, that doth not deſpair of his own: — <hi>when the Law came, ſin revived and I dyed.</hi> 4. The Promiſes about the Being and exerciſe of Grace, are before the Knowledge of them: An Act preſuppoſes an Object; there are many things in our Souls we are ignorant of, or doubtful about: Whether Freedom be an Attribute of the Will, or rather of the Man? How far it is active or paſſive? Whether it can form an Idea never impreſs'd? Whether it be capable of Traduction, or another Soul may be propagated from it, or created out of it? And how long may we be ignorant of the Acceſſes and Receſſes of the Spirit of God, with which is his Language to it, and what Influences ſpeak a State paſt the danger of final Relapſing. 5. The Promiſes that give a Capacity, before them that fill and ſatisfie it: It is not orderly acting, to put an Eſtate in a Minors power, one under Age. Our Lord took two of the moſt ripe and early Children that ever this World afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and gave the World an Experiment of their Unfitneſs for enjoying the Comforts and raviſhing Enjoyments of the other World; <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> they were both confounded, they knew not what they ſaid, nor what they heard. 6. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes ſuited to our Need rather than Deſire: Our Deſire is corrupted and feveriſh; we often long for what would injure us, but our Saviour minds our Salvation firſt; <hi>this is all my Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and all my Deſire.</hi> 7. The Lord reſerves to himſelf ſome Monuments of his former deſpotical Right, a Sovereign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the diſpoſal of ſome Bleſſings in the Covenant; as about all outward Bleſſings, Plenty, Peace, Proſperity; about the Time of effectual Calling into the Covenant; about the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:44461:14"/>under Legal Frames, or a ſpirit of Bondage; there is a <hi>May be</hi> as to many Mercies; in the Fifth Command, <hi>Honour thy Father,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that thy days may be long.</hi> God may give ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mercy for long Life: If a man give a pound of Gold for Lead, he breaks not Promiſe, eſpecially where more need of it.</p>
            <p>The Second Part of the Matter of the Covenant is its Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and Commands: There is a beautiful Order alſo obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble among them. 1. In a ſuitableneſs to our Condition: He lays not heavy Burdens and galling Yoaks on the Necks of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but the moſt eaſie and facile; the Work and Employ of Angels, who perpetually praiſe God, is not charg'd on us, or ſuch Perſonal War with Devils, the chaining and reſtraining of them: We are not fit to be God's Inſtruments in the great Revolutions and Meſſages they are, nor are the ſame things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd of Infants and adult Perſons, Pagans and Chriſtians. 2. Precepts about our Life precede them about our Work; Faith that is the Appetite we live by, is firſt Commanded; Chriſt is the true Bread of Life, and Faith the fix'd and determin'd Deſire on him. Parents have as much Care about feeding their Children as afterwards when Men about their Calling and Trade. The ſubject of Faith is Man's Appetite, and Deſire that is the faculty it reſides in, the Gift of Faith is the Preſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Objects or forming Idea's of God in Chriſt, that deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines this deſire alone upon him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. <hi>Who will ſhew us any good?</hi> there's the Faculty, the Soul of Man as paſſive and reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pient, <hi>Lord lift on me the Light of thy Countenance;</hi> there it's determin'd by Faith, that is the Exerciſe of Faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Faith is the evidence of things not ſeen;</hi> there the Object deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining it the Gift of Faith, the way it is wrought is by preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Objects immediately to the Mind, the kindly entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe Objects is our Duty, and our firſt Duty, and the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Self-preſervation or Maintenance: We quench the Spirit who works them, we provoke him if we do not. 3. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts about External Ordinances precede Internal and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Exerciſe, <hi>Phil. Work in and about your own Salvation;</hi> as <hi>Camero</hi> well tranſlates it, to which Ability of Spiritual Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance is annexed, <hi>I will work in you to will and to do.</hi> 1. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances keep the mind from Diſtraction with worldly buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; then our minds are retir'd to contemplate ſpiritual Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:44461:15"/>only, they are helps to keep us from quenching the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. 2. Hence Ordinances are the Means of working Faith, <hi>Before they call I will anſwer, while they are yet ſpeaking I will hear.</hi> The Spirit preſents the Idea's, of which the Words are ſigns to the Mind, <hi>Faith comes by hearing;</hi> therefore People ought to be Careful of their Choice of a Miniſtry, Underſtanding, Sound, and whom the Lord has ſent, to whom he has given a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; thus the Word becomes the Seed of Regeneration, for <hi>beholding in this Glaſs the Glory of the Lord, we are chang'd into the ſame Image,</hi> 2 Cor. 3. It's Satans Concluſion for deſerted Souls to forſake Ordinances, or to abſtain for want of Grace, and yet to continue in them without obtaining Grace is to loſe their end. 4. Precepts about forbearing ſin, Mortification, are before Practice of Godlineſs, <hi>Ceaſe to do evil, learn to do well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. An harmonious Order is ſeen in the Relation of theſe two to one another. 1. In the ſtrictneſs of the Relation: The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation between God and the Creature is as ſoon broken and diſſolved as this, they are inſeparably, perpetually and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally united; no man has a right to the Promiſes that is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Obligation to the Precepts: If a Man lives holily, never queſtion his right to the Promiſes; if a Man has a Right to one Promiſe, he has a Right to all. 2. In the Sweetneſs and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of the Relation. (1.) There are more Promiſes than Commands; the Duty is but an Acknowledgment, a Quit-rent, there are Promiſes for Ability, Exerciſe, Perſeverance, Rewards to every Command. (2.) There is a Priority in the Promiſes, a Stock, ſome Talents, before we Trade. (3.) An Uſefulneſs: We have Ability to Obey from the Promiſe, we have Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge what to do from the Precept: We have the Motive of Reward from the Promiſe, we have the Light and Conduct about the way from the Precept: We are kept from Deſpair by the Promiſe, and preſerv'd from Preſumption by the Command: We were undone if the Covenant wanted its Precepts.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) The <hi>Third</hi> thing the Order of the Covenant is diſcernable in, is about its Ends. 1. God's Glory. 2. Chriſt's Honour. 3. Sinners Salvation. For the firſt, God has his Sovereignty Exalted in the Obedience of his Son, for he and we, his Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and ours are both enjoyned in this Covenant; it's more Glory to have ſuch a Subject than ten Thouſands of Angels; his Wiſdom in its Contriv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce how to ſave his own Juſtice and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:44461:15"/>Truth, and yet ſave the Rebel; to be Juſt and Juſtifier of the Ungodly, is a Wonder of Wiſdom: His Juſtice in his Son's Sufferings, his Mercy in Sinners Salvation. 2. Chriſt's Honour is highly Exalted: It's a Queſtion among Divines, whether any Creature ſhould ever have been ſo nighly United to God as that Humane Nature is, if Man had not fallen; if not, what an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to all the Humane Nature, eſpecially the Man Jeſus! ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe there ſhould have been, what an Honour for a Man to be in ſuch an Office, the King of Kings and Lord of Lords, one Mediator, the Angels Sovereign and Sinners Saviour, to have a Fulneſs not only for himſelf but all Creatures! How wonderful is his Condeſcending Love, who by Union and Birth thus high, and yet became as a <hi>Worm and no Man,</hi> and his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted Glory, who was <hi>as a Root out of a dry ground,</hi> the Scorn and Contempt of the People, and became higher than the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and Holyer than the Angels, the Viſible Image of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible God, in his Incommunicable Attributes, to have Life in himſelf, an Independent Life when once given, the Wiſdom of God, and the Power of God, all the Works of God being managed by him. 3. Sinners Salvation: It is wonderfully or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to render their Salvation 1. Poſſible. 2. Eaſie. 3. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. 4. Suitable. The apparent Repugnancies were either from the Law, Law-giver, Surety or Sinner. 1. The <hi>Law</hi> threatned preſent Death, but not Eternal, <hi>In the day thou eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely dye:</hi> He did Dye, the Eternity was founded on the Perpetuity of ſinning and Heinouſneſs of the Crime, not on the Letter of the Law; it ſpoke nothing againſt an Intervening Surety after the Sinner was once dead, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him from that Death; <hi>It is appointed for all Men once to dye;</hi> but the Law ſpoke nothing againſt a Reſurrection. 2. The <hi>Law-giver</hi> was ſatisfi'd, ſince his Truth in the Law was ſav'd, ſince the Obedience and Sufferings of the Mediator did ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently evince the Holineſs and Juſtice of the the Governour. 3. As to the <hi>Surety,</hi> having his Life wholly in his own Power, it was lawful for him to dye; and ſince it was in his Power to Redeem his Brethren, to re-eſtabliſh the Order of Divine Government, to glorifie his Maker more than any thing done by Creatures yet could, there was a becomingneſs that he ſhould; Decency makes a thing in ſome reſpect a Duty: It was in the Power of his Hand to relieve his Brethren. We cannot thoroughly
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:44461:16"/>Love our Brethren without doing what we can for Relief to their Miſery: His Incarnation was an act of Choice, but once Man, and made under the Law, the Love of his Brethren was a Duty. 4. As to the <hi>Sinner,</hi> it's not only made poſſible but eaſie, for tho Juſtification and Sanctification were both im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to Man, the ſatisfying for paſt Guilt, or the ceaſing from ſin, yet Chriſt having done both, no more remains but our accepting of him for our Mediator, and ſuffering his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to do in us what he will; a Self-denyal, a doing nothing is our principal Duty. The <hi>Sureneſs</hi> of our <hi>Salvation</hi> is to be next ſpoken to, and the Suitableneſs of it conſiſts in the ſtrict Union between the Commands and Promiſes, Holineſs and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs muſt go together.</p>
            <p>The Sixth Property is the <hi>Sureneſs</hi> of it, ſo ordered and ſo guarded nothing can break it: 1. The clear <hi>Aſſertions</hi> of the Spirit of Truth confirms this: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.3. <hi>The ſure Mercies of David.</hi> Jer. 33.20. <hi>If my Covenant with Day and Night can be broken, ſo that they ſhould ceaſe, then may alſo my Covenant with David be broken.</hi> 2. The <hi>Nature</hi> of the Covenant confirms this; for there is nothing in the Matter impoſſible or unlawful: Not the former, for the Promiſes are ſo ordered that they render the Commands eaſie; not the latter, for the Will of God is the Meaſure of Duty to us; and tho' its Duties are inconſiſtent with our praeingagements in a Covenant with Hell and Death, yet that Covenant being unlawful, and its works contrary to what's our Duty antecedently to this, it no way renders this Covenant unſure. 3. The <hi>Party</hi> of the Covenant, GOD, the whole of it depending on Him, not us; if we conſider his Mindfulneſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.5. <hi>He will ever be mindful of his Covenant,</hi> &amp;c. his Power, Righteouſneſs, Wiſdom, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can fail that he has undertaken: And if we conſider the Form of the Covenant, he has undertaken all; Faith bears the room or place of a Condition in the Covenant of Grace; but this very thing makes it loſe the proper Nature of one, that, It is <hi>Gods Gift,</hi> Eph. 2.8. 1. The Beginning and Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1. 2. The Growth of it; <hi>Lord increaſe our Faith.</hi> 3. The Exerciſe of it; <hi>I believe, Lord help my unbelief:</hi> But if Faith ſhould fail, the Unbelief of Man will not render the Faith of God of none effect; tho' we <hi>believe not, yet he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth faithful, he will not deny himſelf,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.13. but that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:44461:16"/>he ſecures that it ſhall not, Jer. 32.40. <hi>They ſhall not depart from me.</hi> Hoſ. 14.5. <hi>He ſhall grow as the Lilly. I have prayed for thee that thy Faith ſhall not fail.</hi> 4. The Foundations of this Covenant demonſtrates its ſureneſs. The Decrees of God: The Love of God: The Death of Chriſt. (1.) The Decrees of God: Our duty is founded on his Legiſlative Will; the Commands contain what we ſhould doe, but the Promiſes are Reſults of his Purpoſes, what God will do: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. This is Gods decree, That the <hi>Heathen</hi> ſhould be Chriſts <hi>Inheritance,</hi> and the <hi>Ends of the Earth</hi> his <hi>Poſſeſſion.</hi> And ſince Promiſes and Purpoſes are of ſo nigh a Kindred, it's not ſo impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to ſay Purpoſes give a Right that needs to be ſtigma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd with the Brand of Error and Hereſie. (2.) The Love of God. <hi>I have loved thee with an everlaſting Love:</hi> Nothing can hinder the impetuous Endeavours of Love among Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: <hi>Love is ſtrong as Death, the Coals thereof have a moſt vehement flame.</hi> If theſe ſhadows of divine Love have ſuch an Influence and Power to remove all Impediments that obſtruct its deſire, what can reſiſt divine Love? (3.) The Death of Chriſt; this was the Fruit of the former: <hi>God ſo loved the World</hi> as <hi>to give Him</hi> to Redeem it, and what then will he not do for it? <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13. Will ever he withhold the Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, or any part of the Purchaſe, ſince he gave his Son to dye a Sacrifice, that Love might communicate it ſelf in a conſiſtence with the Meaſures of Wiſdom and Rules of Juſtice. 5. The Sealing of the Covenant renders it ſure: The Death of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. the Oath of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. the Earneſt of the Spirit, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13. the external ſealing Ordinances, are all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming Seals to render their Conſolation ſolid and ſtrong, that have fled to this Covenant as a Refuge. 6. The Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant its having both Date and day of Payment annex'd. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Chronology contains the one, and the Prophetical <hi>Aera</hi>'s contain the other, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.13. <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.2. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.12. There is a due Time, a fit Time, an appointed Time for every Perſon, Meaſure of Grace and Condition of the Church, and the Lord will never be <hi>ſlack concerning his Coming,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. he will not let any time be loſt. The Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the time as to particular Perſons he reſerves as a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret to himſelf, but the Time of Deliverances and Fulfillments of the Promiſes to the Church, he hath more communicated,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:44461:17"/>and the Neglect of ſtudying them muſt flow from an unconcerned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs about her Affairs: There are two things certain about them. (1.) That there is a ſet time for great Promiſes to the Church. (2.) That many of them have their ſet times revealed; the Four hundred thirty years from the Covenant made with <hi>Abraham</hi> to the Coming out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> the Seventy Years from the beginning of the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Captivity to the end of it; the Four hundred and Ninety to the Coming of Chriſt in the Fleſh: So the One thouſand two hundred Sixty dayes, Forty two Months, the Time, Times, and half Time. But ſuch is our Infirmity and weakneſs, that we may doubt of the time when it is on the very brink of fulfilment, as our Fathers did. 7. It is as ſure as the Covenant of Redemption, which was made between Infallible Perſons: For tho they may be conſidered as diſtinct Covenants, yet the one is Foundation and Security for the other, it is like a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent Surety entring a Covenant with the Creditor, to pay for paſt Debt, and engage as Surety for future Credit; ſo that the Suretiſhip in the Covenants between God and Man, is what he undertakes in his own perſonal Covenant with God. <hi>He hath given him for a Covenant to the People.</hi> It is more ſure than the Covenant of Nature, with Day and Night, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for by Miracles the one be diſordered, but all Miracles are to confirm the Covenant of Grace, and aſſure us of its Truth.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Seventh</hi> Property is its <hi>perfection</hi> or <hi>Allneſs</hi> as to <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> and <hi>Deſire.</hi> There are two things to be premiſed to the proof of it. (1.) The difference between theſe two <hi>Alls.</hi> (2.) In what reſpects the Covenant contains them. 1. The <hi>All</hi> of Salvation is leſs than the <hi>All</hi> of Deſire; Pardon and Sinleſneſs will compleatly ſave us, but not ſatisfie us. <hi>Adam</hi> needed not Salvation before he periſhed, but his Deſire was not compleatly ſatisfied. 2. They differ as Food and Phyſick, as the Religion of ſinleſs Angels and ſinful Men, the one is Vital, and becoming a perfect Healthful State; the other is Medicinal, a remedial Religion, to reſtore us to Life and Health; the Deſires of the one are often to be corrected, mortified; the other to be nouriſhed, and ſtill ſtrengthen'd, the Deſire or Appetite ſtill increaſing with the Reception. (2.) In what reſpects the Covenant contains them. 1. The Revelation and Diſcovery of them. 2. It's the Inſtrument of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:44461:17"/>Conveyance, and gives a Right to them: And hence 3. It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>s the Soul with aſſur'd Hope of them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23. <hi>We are ſav'd by Hope.</hi> For the third thing, the proof of this; the proof of the latter contains the former, as the greater Bleſſing doth the leſſer. Man can never have his deſire ſatisfi'd untill he be fav'd: And indeed the Diſeaſe of Hunger and uneaſie craving will alſo be remov'd when we are ſav'd: For ſuch a deſire is a great piece of Miſery. But a plenteous Redemption will bring a plentiful Salvation; the <hi>fulneſs of Grace and Truth</hi> that is in Chriſt will remove the Emptineſs of the Creature, and all is contained in the Covenant. 1. All that is in the Earth is promiſed, Gold, Silver, fine Linnen, Feaſts of <hi>fat things,</hi> Honey, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>All things are yours.</hi> God thinks not this Old World good enough, therefore he will make it New for them, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 2. Heaven alſo, and all that is in it; and this is more than we deſire; we would never have dream'd of it, if the Promiſes had not contain'd it, and given ſome preventive diſcovery. <hi>For Eye hath not ſeen, nor Ear heard, nor hath it entred into the Heart of Man to</hi> conſider <hi>what,</hi> &amp;c. Iſa. 64.4. 3. All in God. <hi>I am thy God,</hi> contains more than any man can infer from it: Who would have dream'd of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding a Reſurrection out of it? <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.32. Chriſt being ours, contains all our Salvation; and God being ours contains all our Deſire; they are both ours by vertue of this Covenant that contains a Covenant of Peace and War, they are offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive and defenſive with us, all our Enemies theirs, Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency is on our ſide. In a Covenant of Traffick and Commerce all they have in their All-ſufficiency, by ſending of our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers the Ships of Deſire, may be obtain'd freely. In a Marriage Covenant, <hi>There will I give thee my Loves;</hi> that is beyond all. It is on this account <hi>Gen.</hi> 33.9.11. that <hi>Jacob</hi> retorts on <hi>Eſau</hi>'s <hi>Enough, I have All,</hi> becauſe God was his God, thô <hi>Eſau</hi> more Riches: The Engliſh wrong the word, tranſlating it <hi>Enough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude this with theſe Motives. 1. We <hi>may</hi> do it. 2. We <hi>muſt</hi> do it, as a Duty and a Mean. 3. Whenever we doe, God accepts, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.17. It would never enter into our Hearts without his Spirit: Our ſaying, <hi>I am thine,</hi> is but the Echo of his Voice. 4. God delights in it, <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.24. 5. We <hi>can</hi> do it: (1.) From Ability already received. It is a true Article of the Synod of <hi>Dort, That every Man may do
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:44461:18"/>more good than he does;</hi> though we have no ſpiritual Power by Nature, and I doubt much whether any Moral Power either. For there is a great difference between what Man actually is by Heavens common Gifts, and what Man is by Nature. All the External Ordinances of Religion lye under our Power, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaining from External Vices, Lying, Swearing, Murther, Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery; elſe the Magiſtrate could not juſtly puniſh Criminals. We may, as <hi>Job,</hi> make <hi>a Covenant with</hi> our <hi>Eyes,</hi> and ſo with all our Senſes and Organs, that lye under the power of our Will; when reſtraint is removed from Conſcience, often they lye under our Power to employ them about things that tend to our Souls good: We can covenant to do what is within our Power, to God as well as we do to Men; and would we have God to work Miracies where there is no need? to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe a Supernatural Power, where Natural Powers can do? Which were to diſorder the Harmonious Method of his beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Providence, to work Extraordinary in us what Ordinary aſſiſtance can do: He has promiſed Special Grace on our enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging in this, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12, 13. <hi>Work out your own Salvation,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>I will work in you,</hi> &amp;c. He commands that we ſhould try him in this very point, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Prove me now herewith, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> All Believers have ſet their <hi>Probatum</hi> to it, that God was always faithful to his Promiſe. (2.) Becauſe we engage not in our Own ſtrength, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.24. <hi>Surely ſhall one ſay, In the Lord have I Righteouſneſs and Strength:</hi> Chriſt is Man as well as God, and in his Office as Mediator he ſtands on our ſide as well as Gods: <hi>Behold I and the Children which God hath given me:</hi> He is called the <hi>whole Covenant</hi> Himſelf, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.6.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gilleſpy</hi> on <hi>the Covenant,</hi> p. 467.</note> In Practicals we commonly fall ſhort in giving Chriſt his own room in the Covenant. 1. He is the Root and Original of it: We ought not to deal with God as if it had its firſt riſe when it firſt entred into our Heart. 2. He is the principal Party; we ſhould not drudge him after us as an Aſſiſtant, and we the principal Creditors of the Promiſes, and the principal Debtors of Duty, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.21. If we give Chriſt his own place, we will find Covenanting with God an eaſie and comfortable thing. The Lord grant we may find it ſo. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
